<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of a portable barometer, with reasons and rules for the use of it how to weigh the air, measure its height, and foretell all the alteration of weather, the constitution of the atmosphere, and how the effluvia keep off the airs gravitation : with a new account and experiments, how rain, snow, winds, frost, thunder, lightning, hurricans and tornados are produced, and an inquiry, whether the planetary beams or influence can cause an alteration of weather, to be foretold by them : with a sensible demonstration of their influences and the insufficiency of all hygroscopes, thermometers, and other inventions, to discover the alterations of weather by : and lastly, rules and experiments for the certain knowledge of all the alterations of weather, both in quantity and quality / by Gust. Parker, Med.</title>
            <author>Parker, Gustavus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1399</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11875921</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11875921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50242</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56139)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50242)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 504:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of a portable barometer, with reasons and rules for the use of it how to weigh the air, measure its height, and foretell all the alteration of weather, the constitution of the atmosphere, and how the effluvia keep off the airs gravitation : with a new account and experiments, how rain, snow, winds, frost, thunder, lightning, hurricans and tornados are produced, and an inquiry, whether the planetary beams or influence can cause an alteration of weather, to be foretold by them : with a sensible demonstration of their influences and the insufficiency of all hygroscopes, thermometers, and other inventions, to discover the alterations of weather by : and lastly, rules and experiments for the certain knowledge of all the alterations of weather, both in quantity and quality / by Gust. Parker, Med.</title>
                  <author>Parker, Gustavus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 102 [i.e. 100], [4], 103-104, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Haws ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Addenda ([4] p.) inserted between p. 102 and p. 103.</note>
                  <note>"The table or contents" on p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Patent Office Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Barometers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50242:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50242:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF A Portable Barometer, WITH Reaſons and Rules For the Uſe of it.</p>
            <p>How to Weigh the Air, Meaſure its Height, and foretell all the alteration of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the Conſtitution of the Atmoſphere, and how the Effluvia keep off the Air's Gravitation: with a New Account and Experiments, how Rain, Snow, Winds, Froſt, Thunder, Lightning, Hurricans and Tornado's are produced: And an inquiry, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Planetary Beams or Influence can cauſe an alteration of weather, to be foretold by them:</p>
            <p>With a ſenſible Demonſtration of their Influences, and the inſufficiency of all Hygroſcopes, Thermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters, and other Inventions, to diſcover the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations or Weather by.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Rules and Experiments for the certain knowledge of all the alterations of Weather, both in Quantity and Quality.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST. PARKER, Med.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Haws</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> MDCXCX</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:50242:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50242:2"/>
            <head>THE Preface.</head>
            <p>THE buſineſs of a Portable Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rometer have been the endeavours of ſeveral Men above Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Years laſt paſt: To find out ſome way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to put the Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver
<pb facs="tcp:50242:3"/>Glaſs into a ſecure Travelling Poſture: at laſt they got a way to tye a piece of Leather over the Ciſtern and round the Tube, and ſuch they called their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Barometers, which the <hi>Philoſophical Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions</hi> ſaies, are no ways to be truſted to, by reaſon of their Intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Errors, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides are indeed no ways Portable: which this of mine is to every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that can but walk,
<pb facs="tcp:50242:3"/>and will whether they will or not ſhew any alteration of Weather, and ſeveral other things beſides: But this ſhort Account being altogether new, and I believe the firſt that ever came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad of this nature, conſiſting only of Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments and Diſcoveries of this Inſtrument, it will I hope (from friends eſpecially) want the leſs Apology, both for the Stile, Matter, and manner which is not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:50242:4"/>ſo ſmoth well digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ordered in a thing that never was before, as it may be a ſecond time: And I hope the confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the uſefulneſs of theſe Barometers in all the following and many other Diſcoveries will excuſe the reſt, not only in what concerns the true Nature, Quality, Temper and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Air, as to its ſelf and the alterations of the Weather, but all other Liquids as well
<pb facs="tcp:50242:4"/>which may thus be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ways both weighed and meaſured at the ſame time in their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and thereby diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover many particular qualifications very hard and difficult if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible by any other means, and thereby alſo in time give a Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the true Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem of all Natural Bodies. And being thus led to the knowledge of their Conſiſtence will be
<pb facs="tcp:50242:5"/>conducted from thence to their Prima Materia, and ſo to the Grand Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem of the Great World. But as there are ſome who have gained the way of making others little upon Truſt, ſo they will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the news of any that undertake to undeceive them, and will neither give themſelves, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers leave to conſider what another have done: Yet if they will ſet to work and Merit their
<pb facs="tcp:50242:5"/>own Encomiums with <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> they ſhall have every thing due to their Characters from.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guſ<hi rend="sup">ts.</hi> Parker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:50242:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50242:6"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF A Portable Barometer.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Firſt what the Portable Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter is, the Conſtitution of the Atmoſphere, and how the Effluvia keep off the Airs Gravitation, and are the cauſe of the variation of its weight.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat I have to offer about a Portable Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rometer I once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſhew the world in another manner, but ſince
<pb facs="tcp:50242:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50242:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50242:8"/>that could not be I am unwilling by reaſon of the extraordinary ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice it may be applied to in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, Hydroſtaticks and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks, they ſhould know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, yet know no reaſon after a great deal of Labour and Charge to give it away, but could rather wiſh there were ſomething ordered for a preſent reward, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the worth of every diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, whereby every improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would immediately receive a thouſand improvements if it were capable, and the World the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit at the ſame time: And for the Philoſophical Reaſons of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of theſe things from Authors I never ſaw any, either of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors or this, and as I ſuppoſe the thing is New, ſo I know nothing but what reaſon has taught me in the uſe of it, for about two years and a half. Therefore it cannot be ſuppoſed the Method, Reaſons or Rules ſhould be ſo ſmooth, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and Perfect the firſt time as they may be afterward, if I live
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50242:8"/>and do well to make another Edition.</p>
               <p>The Portable Barometer is an Inſtrument that weighs the Air, meaſures its Height, and foretells all the alterations of Weather both in Quantity and Quality, which for the better underſtanding it will be convenient to tell the reaſons, which I ſhall do in ten Particulars, Then ſhew the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in its uſe, and ſettle the Rules, for there is no alteration of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is not preceeded by an alteration of the weight of the Air, both for Heat and Cold, as well as Wet and Dry, which comes to paſs in this manner.</p>
               <p>The continual motion of the Parts of Matter, of which all things are compoſed, and from whence they encreaſe and decay, begets a mighty Emancipation of Atoms, with conſtant Emanations from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part of all ſorts of Bodies, which being preſſed on every ſide
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50242:9"/>by the Univerſal Fluid of Air gives them particular bounds, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute an Atmoſphere or Sphere of Attoms to every Body (and is thereby alſo the cauſe of Electri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Attractions) therefore the great Globe of Earth and Water, with all its conſiſtent Bodies muſt needs have very Copious Effluvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums, and ſo make a very large Atmoſphere, being by an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Motion driven from every part of the whole, as far as the Power of that Motion, and the Preſſure of the Air will give leave, which by that Preſſure and their own weight are again returned like random-ſhot, from whence they are ſent: This Sphere of Atoms (or at leaſt our Hemiſpherical part thereof) is ſometimes filled with more and leſs Emanations by the inequality of that Motion ſeveral Undulations, particular Eddies, and the Effluvia Circulations, which in like manner does more or leſs keep off the Airs Gravitation whereby a Cylinder of the Air
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50242:9"/>cannot weigh ſo much in wet or Winds Weather as it does in dry Weather (and not as <hi>John Smith</hi> tells us by his Principle of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, that the Air is lighter by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mixt with watery vapors, tho a thouſand times heavier than its ſelf, and mixes Water with Rectified Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Wine for a Demonſtration in his <hi>Horological Diſquiſitions</hi> pag. 75.) I ſay Winds as well as Wet keep off the Airs Gravitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Winds alſo being only humid bodies ſufficiently dilated and by that Expanſive force the ſtrugling Atoms as ſtrangely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated, with numerous and powerful Attacks from multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of freſh Emancipations and Eruptions from our Aeolian Globe muſt needs keep off the Air's Gravitation, much more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pacide Vapors (as I ſhall further Demonſtrate in the third and fifth Chapters following) which in the Common Barome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter make very conſiderable altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, tho there be no Rain,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50242:10"/>and are eaſily diſcovered by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Hygroſcopes by their ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Gravities, as I ſhall ſhew in the tenth Chapter. Thus our Aeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Effluvia do not only keep off the Gravitation of the Air, but are the cauſe of the variation of its weight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50242:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>How Rain and Snow are Generated and Produced, and why they make a Cylinder of Air lighter, and yet any other particular parcel of Air much heavier.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat I have to ſay upon the Contents of this Chapter, is not of the prime cauſe of Rain and Snow, but only a ſhort account of their Generation and Production, in relation to their affections of the Atmoſphere, for the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the nature and uſe of the Barometer. Rain and Snow, then are generated of the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: But for diſtinction I will firſt give an account of Rain, and then of Snow. Rain is generated of the Effluviums that conſtitute our Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raqueous Atmoſphere, being by their Emancipated motion in a certain
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50242:11"/>part thereof driven towards the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of the Sun's reflections into a cooler Region, they ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſe in ſome little part firſt, which Condenſation immediately makes room for the natural Elaſticity of the Air, which as ſoon begins to carry a long with it all the other Effluvia round about to the firſt Condenſation, where being by this Elaſtick force, firſt brought from all the neighbouring parts, the Efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Air then runs down by its own weight and Elaſticity from every ſide to a vaſt extent, where being heaped and crowded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they not only fall by their Innate Gravity, but by the ſame motion of Air (which now is Wind) are ſent down ſometimes with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream violence, and thus not only the neighbouring Atoms are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſed in a little Cloud and ſmall Showers, but the whole Hemiſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Effluvia are driven and drawn together and diſcharged upon a whole Country or national Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon oftentimes, till the whole half Atmoſphere is emptied of all thoſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50242:11"/>Vapors, and then having made a Current from every part beyond, all the other Emanations that are raiſed in other parts of the world as readily flow hither, to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged here in continual Rains for a long time together, till by a piarticuler Condenſation in ſome other Place, the courſe is altered and the Current turned, and then it may be Dry as long; the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſtream of Atoms being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away to other Places to be diſcharged there.</p>
               <p>The difference between ſtorms or a little wet, and laſting ſettled Rains, is that in the firſt Emanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated Atoms being not ſo thick or Copious as at other times in their elevating Motions, become Bounded by Particular Eddies of Air, which drives them ſo cloſe together, that by this means they are formed into Clouds; and by their being driven yet cloſer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, by the Power and ſtrength of theſe Eddies, and the Addition of freſh Matter: The ſmall Atoms fall ſo faſt one into another by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50242:12"/>Cold and compreſſure that very large Drops are Immediately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced and ſent Down with more or leſs violence according to the Diſpoſition of their Motion, the Seaſon, and Air.</p>
               <p>But in ſettled Rains, the Efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Vapors, having for ſome time before been continually filling our Hemeſphere, from all parts without any diſcharge, in a ſtill and quiet manner without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing the Air; at laſt receive a Condenſation as above in ſome particular part, which Immediately makes way for the Airs Elaſticity.</p>
               <p>But being now every where filled, which theſe Vapors cannot unbend or move ſo faſt; yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually brings the Neighbouring Vapors, and ſo are gently and continually ſent down as long as they laſt-</p>
               <p>Snow is generated of the ſame Effluvium's or ſmall peices of moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture when the Sun is at a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Diſtance, and the Country pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with Hills, Mountains, and Latitudes. The Calorifick Beams
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50242:12"/>being eaſily hindred by them, or not tended far enough for the other, together with the Aſſiſtance of the Contrary Motions, or Interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Beams of the other Stars; or obſtructed by the Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Effluvia that murales or or walls the whole Atmoſphere, or by contrary currants of Air, or Winds: and the Heat being thus or any other ways kept off, and the Effluvious Vapours continuing their Pneumatick Motions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great preſſure, they are not condenſed into Drops, but are frozen in their own ſhapes, in ſome little part firſt: which is quickly extended to all the reſt by the Frigorifick Saline, Particls as they uſe to tell us, univerſally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed and mixed with theſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms. But rather by the former privations, as will be further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated in the 6 Chapter. Then being driven a little cloſer they fall by their own weight in bigger or leſſer Flakes, and with more or leſs driving according as the Motion, Cold and Preſſure is. Then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50242:13"/>as for Hail, that is ſeldom any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ways than in Storms, and is a kind of half frozen Snow and Rain mixed together. The manner of its generation and Production may be eaſily conceived by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I have given of Rain and Snow with better ſatisfaction than what they uſe to tell us of the drops freezing after they fall from the Clouds, which is almoſt impoſſible. But this being not ſo directly to my purpoſe, I ſhall ſay no more of it, but only demonſtrate how Rain and Snow which thus thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens and fills the Air, yet make a Cylinder thereof much lighter, but any other particular parcel of Air much heavier. The reaſon why Snow and Rain make a Cylinder of Air lighter, is that the Effluvious vapours that conſtitute the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere and of which it conſiſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo very numerous from every part of Matter, and ſo conſtantly and powerfully ſent out, that they not only make particular ſtreams from the more fluid parts, but an univerſal ſtream from the whole
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50242:13"/>Globe of Earth and Water, and all other conſiſtent Bodies whatever. This univerſal ſtream or flood of Vapors being thus united in all parts of the world, make an intire ſcreen of condenſed or thickened Matter to a great thickneſs, being near a thouſand times more ſolid than Air, before they appear in Clouds, and therefore muſt needs keep off or ſtop the Airs penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thereby its Gravitation, which yet does not require a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rain or Snow, for a little that comes by particular Currents or Eddies in Storms will do it, for they being of no great height, want no great extent, to hinder both the direct and collateral preſſure of the Air, as has been obſerved by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Barometers in a little diſtance. Thus the Ethereal Particles are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways hindred by theſe Emanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, at all times, but much more in wet than in dry weather, and the nearer the Earth's Surface, the more they are obſtructed, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the little heights of ſmall Hills, by the ſame Barometers, ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50242:14"/>that it is impoſſible a Cylinder of Air ſhould weigh ſo much in wet, as it does in dry weather, which I ſhall now demonſtrate by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments alſo.</p>
               <div type="experiments">
                  <head>Experiments in weighing the Air.</head>
                  <p>In weighing the Air with the Portable Barometer the Weights may and do conſiſt of Ounces, Drachms, Scruples and Grains, and may as well be Pounds, or Hundreds, but will be moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to have them of one De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, and the bigger or more Weights we uſe, the greater will be the variation of the ſmaller parts (if the Balance be good) to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell the laſt as well as other altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of weather by, which with ſmall weights except the Balance be very nice, will not be caſie to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh ſo many minute variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as all the alterations of weather will require; I have therefore a weight conſiſting of, or divided into 2000 equal parts for the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or Center of variation, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50242:14"/>have not yet obſerved the weight of Air to vary full 60 ſuch parts, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove or below that number, that is 120 in all, ſo if the weight be bigger the variations will be more, as this of 2000 is 120, if it were 4000, the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation would be 240 ſuch parts, which is near ten times as much as in the Common Barometer, but if it be but 1000, the variations will not be above 60 ſuch parts, which is 3 times as much as the common ones, and to be leſs will not be ſo ſerviable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>January</hi> 3. 1698/9 a Cylinder of Air weighed but 1951, having been very wet the day before, and rained all the night preſceeding, and now extream dark thick weather, but no rain this thrid day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 4. it weighed 1958, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cloudy, but no Rain this day nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 6. it weighed 1964, when it rained all the day abundance.</p>
                  <p>The firſt of theſe times the Common Barometer was ſomething below much Rain, the next the Quickſilver ſtood at much Rain, and in the laſt one diviſion above much Rain.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50242:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50242:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:50242:16"/>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50242:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 12. 1698, a Cylinder of Air weighed 2025, it was very fair, clear and dry.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 3. 1698, a Cylinder weighed 2022, being very fair clear and dry.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> the 3d. and 4th. 1698, a Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linder of Air weighed 2026, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fair, yet thawing and a hard froſt going away.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt of theſe, the Common Barometer was at fair, and at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond very near, at the laſt ſomewhat above fair.</p>
                  <p>Theſe I believe are ſufficient to prove that a Cylinder of Air does not weigh ſo much in wet as in dry wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but yet a particular parcel of Air as a Quart, Gallon or Buſhel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt needs weigh much heavier in a wet time or tho only miſty, then in a clear Seaſon, it containing ſo many watery Particles every where within our reach, that there is not above one third part of pure Air, if ſo much as I have ſeveral times tried.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 21 and 22. 1698, it rained both days almoſt from morning to night, and ſo much in <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Bedfordſhire,</hi> that the like had not been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50242:17"/>known. On the 21, I took a Braſs <hi>Aeolipile,</hi> which held ſomething more than a Pint and half, a little better than eight and twenty ounces of common well Water, this was made as hot as it would indure, and then the Orifice was very well ſtoped with a firm Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo laid to cool, and when it was through cold, in an exact pair of Scales, it weighed Eight Ounces Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Drachms and a half, the Orifice being then opened to let in the Air, it weighed ſomething above 19 Grains more: a Cylinder of Air at the ſame time weighed 1962, and the Quickſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Glaſs ſtood 4 below Changeable. The 22 in the morning the ſame quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Air weighed near 20 Grains, a Cylinder of Air 1963, and the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-glaſs as before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 2. 1698/9, being a very wet day, when a Cylinder of Air weighed but 1949, the Weather-glaſs at 2 below much Rain, the emptied Aeolipile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained 21 grains and a half of humid Air.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> the 6. following very wet again, yet a Cylinder of Air weighed 1964, the Weather-glaſs three diviſions higher than on the ſecond day, but the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50242:18"/>exhauſted Aeolipile 22 Grains of humid Air this day.</p>
                  <p>Then on the 12th of <hi>Sept.</hi> 1698, when a Cylinder of Air weighed 2025, the Weather Fair, the Aeolipile heat and weighed as before, would now hold but 15 Grains and a half of Air.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 3d following a Cylinder of Air weighed 2022, being very fair and clear, the Weather-glaſs very near the ſame height, the Aeolipile weighed 16 Grains more when the Air was let in then before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> the 4th 1698, a Cylinder of Air weighed 2026, being very fair but a little miſty, the Weather-glaſs a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle above Fair, the exhauſted Aeolipile near 17 Grains more when the Air was let in, then it did before. This I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve is ſufficient to make good the Title of this Chapter, and prove the truth of a Paradox or two, that the Ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is both lighter and heavier in we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> weather, and both heavier and lighte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in dry weather: But there is, nor can be no certainty in the Aeolipilan way as I ſhall demonſtrate in the 10 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to foretell any alteration of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50242:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>How Winds, Storms, Tempeſts, Hurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes and Tornados are produced?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Portable Barometer, being an Inſtrument that diſcovers all the alterations of Weather, it will be convenient to give ſome account of Winds alſo, what they are, and how produced, for they are as well fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen by this as any other ſort of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the reaſon we have had no better knowledge of them, is only for want of a true method in Science, to direct us in all natural obſervations to enlarge and confirm our knowledge, That have kept us from it, therefore what I have to ſay of Winds cannot be expected to be either ſo full or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as what is dilivered of more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Subjects, being not ſo Cogniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our Senſes, but are indeed of a Metaphyſical Nature, of which few I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50242:19"/>ſuppoſe have made any great experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but only given us ſome Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical relations of their ſtrangeneſs, and tho Winds are only the motions of Air, yet their origines are almoſt as various as their motions, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be had from any one cauſe, but we muſt aſcend into the Regions of the Air, and deſcend into the Caverns of the Earth, and Waters of the Sea, to underſtand them, for we can never confine their original to any one effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, nor (I believe) there never was any ſingle Theory yet ſtated, that would reſolve the whole Phaenominon of Winds, which may be generated theſe ſix ways, by Rarefaction, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſure, Elaſticity and Reſilition, or by Subterraneal, or Submarine Erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The univerſal Efficient of the firſt four is chiefly the operations of the Sun Beams upon the Effluvious Air, and that of the other two from Subterranial Vutrano's and Calid Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Mineral Heterogenities, as I ſhall ſucceſſively ſhew.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> by Rarification, that Air may be dilated to 100, 200, nay 13000 times its former extent, as the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50242:19"/>Eſquire <hi>Boyle, Merſennus</hi> and others have experienced without heat, by removing the Circumjacent Preſſure of the other Aerial Particles, but let this or any ſuch Rarefaction be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from what cauſe ſoever, either by the Sun Beams, or any other heat, or Condenſation of ſome particular part, to make room for the natural Expan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of another, the effects will be all one, a Wind muſt inſue by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion of other Air, which by this means crowd and Superonerate the former ſpaces, whereby that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and admirable Emotions of the Atmoſphere is produced, we call Wind, which is more or leſs violent according to the force and extent of the Rarefaction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Compreſſure is another way, by which Winds may be gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, the Effluvious Air being in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual motion, not in one, but ſeveral Currents muſt needs produce very numerous undulations, theſe together, almoſt as many Eddies, whether in pure Air, Efflvious Vapours, or Clouds, which in contrary Currents meet, with more or leſs violence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50242:20"/>to the Bigneſs, Strength, and Denſity of the Matter, by which means the Wind may (as the preſſure is) vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently deſcend Perpendicularly to the Earth, or being reverted by croſs or collateral obſtructions, heaping and preſſing Superonerations, makes as vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent Whirl-winds, Hurricanes or Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadoes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to blow from all the parts of the Compaſs at the ſame time, with amazing Diſploſions, as if the Heavens and the Earth were going to be torn in pieces, by theſe examinating Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts. But their ſeveral Species is not my preſent buſineſs, only the uſe of the Barometer, but if Life and Leiſure ſerve, it may be done in another Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Elaſticity the natural ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineſs of the Air is another cauſe of Winds, for tho we ſuppoſe our At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſphere to be in never ſo ſtill and quiet a poſture, and all things moſt calm and ſedate, yet 'tis impoſſible it ſhould be all of one univerſal conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtency, but muſt contain a great vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of rare and denſe parts, from the Local Diffirances the Emanations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from, either Waters or Marſhes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50242:20"/>or dry Lands, and theſe different de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of fluid Denſities, being upon a juſt and true Aequilibrium, a ſmall ſtrenght of other Elaſtick Particles between, turns them any way, which immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately make room for a numerous ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of other Auxiliaries to a vaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that carries all before them in an impetuous Wind. So that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any Aereal Particle has leave to unbend it ſelf in any poſture, it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately gives way to the other neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Particles Expanſions, and as the motion is made, to others beyond, to a mighty extent, by which means their ſtrength is alſo encreaſed to a mighty proportion, with the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their weight, to their Elaſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo carries all before them to the turning up of the ſtrongeſt Oakes or Buildings, which continue till the Elaſtick Particles are driven to their utmoſt extentions, that the other pacid Particles will yeild to, and then they begin again to curl and fluctuate, and by degrees to ſettle in their native poſtures, and a quiet calm, till freſh cauſes give them new diſturbances.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:50242:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Reſilition of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſphere is another cauſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces wind, the Effluvious Air being eaſily taken and brought into currents by ſeveral Meanders, as well in the upper as in the lower Regions; in the upper by the Sun Beams, or the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular conſtitution, or local poſition of the ſame Effluviums; and in the lower by the Waters in ſeveral Seas and Channels, and alſo with ſeveral Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Valleys by Land, this tender fluid being ſo very tractable, ſo eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſceptible and long retentive of the laſt Impreſſion, that 'tis a kind of a perpetual Automata, which may by theſe or ſeveral other ways be brought into Currents; but yet it is almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible theſe Currents ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in even and uninterrupted Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicular courſes, but muſt be met or obſtructed by ſeveral Clouds and Denſities in the Atmoſphere, Hills, Mountains, the Sun Beams, contrary Currents of Air, Provincial Trade or Eteſian-winds, Maſcarets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> any of which obſtructions forthwith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets this Reſilition, and that more or leſs wind, according to the bigneſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50242:21"/>and ſtrength of the recoyling Protru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Subterraneal eruptions are another cauſe of Winds, which erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are produced by the Calid Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Efferveſcencies of Mineral Heterogeneities that plentifully abound in all parts of the world; and theſe Calid Emotions by the mixtures of the Effluvious Acids from Niter, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Salts, Vitriols, Sulphurs, Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which will immediately heat only with a ſmall quantity of fair water (as Spirits of Niter and Vitriol, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are only their acid ſalts freed from their more Terreſtrial parts, and united with a little Phlegm, mingled with water will do) the ſmall Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eles of which are always at hand, and can never be wanting in no ſuch places. And with bigger additions of other Auxiliaries, are in ſome places aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented to actual fires, by which means their acid Salts are made Alcaline, and ſo furniſh the whole Univerſe with ſufficient matter for Efferveſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and fermenting Calid Emotions by the continual actions and reactions of their Acid and Alcaline Particles,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50242:22"/>as quick Lime and Water, or theſe with Sal Armoniack, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or any Acid Spirit with the aſhes of Wood, Bones, Coals, or other Alcalies will immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately heat and boyl without fire, with ſuch ſtrength and violence, that the ſtrongeſt Veſſel cannot contain them. Thus the Subterraneal Caverns are the Kingdom of <hi>Aeolus,</hi> and Nature's Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Furnaces, where all the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Cranies are Receptacles of Wind, from the internal Vulcano's. Rarefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are continually ſent Night and Day from all thoſe places, and conſtantly diſturb our Atmoſphere more or leſs, in one place or another, by their powerful Propulſions: For the Earth is the firſt Mother of Meteors, and contains all thoſe reſtleſs Spirits and Efferveſcencies, that afterwards raiſe Storms, Tempeſts, Hurricanes, and Tornado's by Sea; ſeveral raging Winds and violent Storms by Land, Thunders and Lightnings in the Air, and Earth-quakes under ground, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently known to come from the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mountains in <hi>China,</hi> the Grotto's in <hi>Calabria</hi> and <hi>Sicily:</hi> The <hi>Alps</hi> and many other places of the World.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:50242:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Submarine eruptions are produced in the ſame manner under the Sea, as the others are under the Ground, and generate Winds as they do, and are called <hi>Procella Coeca,</hi> they break out in a Cloud or Miſt, from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Water, and encreaſe and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe themſelves, till they cover the face of the whole Heavens, and end in moſt dreadful Tempeſts, we have an account of one from our Fleet at <hi>Duncannon,</hi> by the Principal Officers to their Superiours in <hi>England,</hi> related by Eſquire <hi>Boyle,</hi> that in a calm day, there ſuddenly aſcended a black Cloud out of the Water, hard by them, in ſhape and bigneſs of a Barrel, which afterwards ended in ſo hideous and dreadful a Tempeſt, that it forced the Ships to Sea again, in the greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of total deſtruction, and had like to have caſt them away. So in St. <hi>Owen</hi>'s Bay, in the Iſle of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> when never ſo calm, and no Wind ſtirring, theſe ſubmarine Tempeſts often appear, and the roaring of the Waves are heard all over the Iſle, and 20 or 30 miles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France,</hi> and in the River <hi>Dourdongn</hi> near <hi>Bourdeaux;</hi> the Maſcarets ſwell
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50242:23"/>the Water into Mountains, and the People cry out <hi>Garde le Maſcaret</hi> in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, and the calmeſt air. So the Gulf of <hi>Lions</hi> often threatens the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Country with a Deluge, the Lake of <hi>Geneva</hi> and ſeveral other places from the ſame cauſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>That violent Tempeſts, Hurricanes, or Tornadoes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſeldom happen in cold Countries, Winter-ſeaſons, Large Plains or great Seas.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WInds being generated according to the preceding manners, they may conſiſt of almoſt infinite variety of Salts, Sulphurs, Spirits, Mineral and Subterraneous Juices, Damps, and Aeolian Ejections, Miſts and rarified Vapours, Rain, or diſſolved Snow, broken and diſſipated Clouds, or agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated Air, and ſo may be hot, cold, dry, moiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thereby alſo more or leſs laſting or violent according to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50242:23"/>the matter, power and plenty of their Cauſes, yet muſt be raiſed in natural ways from their Fountains or proper Productions, which are very eaſily effected (without recourſe to Occult Cauſes) upon ſo tender a fluid as Air, by the foregoing ways in the preced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapter, and may be as truly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by the Portable Barometer not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this variety, by the alterations they produce in the weight of the Air, but yet violent Winds, Storms, Tempeſts, Hurricanes, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadoes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cannot be ſo eaſily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in cold Countries, hard froſty ſeaſons, large Plains or great Seas, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n warmer Regions, Rockey Countries, or narrow and craggy Seas, for in cold Countries, or froſty Seaſons the Efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Air is too much Condenſed into a kind of fixation, and thereby not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keep the Effluvia in the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, but walls in very Atmoſphere againſt all other Pneumatick Attacks whatever, that the moſt violent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſions of Exotick force can never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order their Perennial Structure, but can only diſplace ſome outward Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, which the ſtanding force of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50242:24"/>reſt will take no notice of, nor can there be any internal diſturbance to diſorder their quiet, for the ſame cold that fixes the Effluvia keeps them ſo, and hinders all other commotions, and alſo ſhuts the pores of the Earth, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Rarefaction of Vapours, and ſtops all manner of Efferveſcencies, and calid Emotions of Subterraneous Mineral Heterogeneous Spirits and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, whereby the Atmoſphere muſt needs be much more quiet and free from theſe raging diſturbances in ſuch places and at ſuch times, than in hot mountainous or rocky places.</p>
               <p>And ſo in large Plains or great Seas there can be nothing to interrupt or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the currents or courſe or the Air, but as it comes, ſo it continues its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, and goes away in a great body to a vaſt diſtance, and meets with nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſilitions nor compreſſions, no Hills, Mountains nor Vulcanos, but is continued almoſt in a perennial Courſe, either with the Sun, Earth or <hi>primum mobile</hi> in all ſuch places as well as the whole Torrid Zone, and ſome degrees on each ſide (except in Rocky Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, narrow Seas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) In Trade,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50242:24"/>Eteſian or Anniverſary Winds, or with the Courſe of the Sea, or Air and Water, as the Levant and Provincial Winds in continued Streams, or at moſt in gentle puffs, and even Gales created by the motion of particular Clouds, ſoft Rains, moderate Storms, or Effluvious Denſities that propell the Air before them in ſuch undulous A ſperities, but muſt be ſomething ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, or a great Complication of cauſes that can ſeldom happen to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Hurricane, Tornado, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in cold Countries great Seas, large Plains, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the chief material efficients are wanting, a powerful Efferveſcency, confuſed Eddies, Tranſverſe Reſiliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſtrong Compreſſions and heaping Superonerations, therefore beſides the freedom from theſe violent ſorts of weather, theſe places muſt needs enjoy more mild and temperate ſeaſons at all times (except heat in the Torrid Zone) than any other, yet heat and cold as well as all other ſorts of weather, are cauſed by the particular temperature, diſpoſition of the Atmoſphere, aſſiſted by the preſence or abſence of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorifick Beams, and conſtitution of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50242:25"/>place, and ſo may be as well foretold by the alterations they make in the weight of the Air as any other ſort of weather, as I ſhall ſhew in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth and Eighth Chapters following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>That they are eaſily foretold, becauſe they produce the greateſt variation in the weight of the Air.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WInds being only the motions or agitations of our Effluvious Air, it may at firſt ſeem ſtrange how they ſhould cauſe ſo great an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the weight thereof above any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of Weather, and will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſurpriſing to ſee a Cylinder of Air that now weighs 2020, or more, in a few hours, not to weigh above 1970 or leſs, and after the Wind is over, in a little longer time, to weigh 2020 a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, or more than it did before, til<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the matter and cauſes are conſidered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If our Hemiſpherical part of the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere continue of an even thickneſs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50242:25"/>and the Effluvia in the ſame poſture, a Cylinder of Air muſt needs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue of the ſame weight; for as there is nothing to alter its denſity, ſo 'tis impoſſible it ſhould alter its gravity, and continuing of the ſame weight, the Effluvia are neither diſperſed, nor more heaped or crowded together, therefore being ſtill there can be no wind, and the longer it holds the greater the calm, if it continues two or three days, a Feather will fall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular from a conſiderable height, ſo that let the weight be what it will, or can, when ever it ſtands it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways calm, which may be further ſaid to be almoſt more than true (if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) for it may continue to increaſe or decreaſe one, two, or three parts in 24 hours, and yet it will continue calm from the higheſt to the loweſt variation.</p>
               <p>And ſo for violent Storms, Tempeſts, Hurricanes and Tornados, they being produced by ſuch means related in the third Chapter, it will be impoſſible any of them ſhould happen, when the weight of the Air does not alter above two, three, four, five, or ſix parts in twenty four hours, nor indeed in half
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50242:26"/>that time, let the alteration be in what part of the variation it will, tho be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 2020 and 1980, five or ſix parts will be near as much as ten in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part: for if it be more than 2020, the Air is too dry or fair, ſo there is nothing to put it into motion, and if it be leſs than 1980, it is too wet, or too much filled, and thickned every where with the Effluvious vapours to receive any ſuch diſturbances; and the reaſons why none of theſe violent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts never come when the weight of the Air alters no faſter, are that the Effluvious Vapours come ſmoothly on, and the Atmoſphere thickens by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and by that means our Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpherical part thereof is gradually filled to a greater or leſſer depth and thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and therefore muſt be leiſurely diſcharged in the manner related in the ſecond Chapter about Rain, for thus our Hemiſphere is ſecured from all manner of violence, from outward at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks, or inward diſturbances of ſtrong Compreſſions, confuſed Eddies, and heaping Superonerations; yet when any of theſe violent Tempeſts do come a calm muſt preceed, and our Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpherical
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50242:26"/>part of the Atmoſphere muſt continue very ſtill for ſome time before (for if the Air be in motion, tho in never ſo gentle a courſe, there can no ſuch thing happen, becauſe it will be carried off by that current as it comes) that their productions may be the better collected and kept together; than in ſuch places as are ſubject to theſe violences, they may be reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly expected from ſome Cavernous Vulcanos, Calid Emotions, ſtrong Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferveſcencies, Subterraneous or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marine Eruptions, either ſingle or complicate, from one or more places, the Emanations being powerfully ſent up perpendicularly from the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon or inclining (as the diſpoſition of the Air is) for a conſiderable time, in ſuch a calm ſeaſon, (like ſmoak from Chimneys) they propel the Air before them, and ſo make room for the other Effluvia that follows with the ſame ſwiftneſs, and the reſt of the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere to unbend, if it inclines with its whole Elaſticity, that makes as quick a current, till the propelled Air being ſtrengthned by a mighty <hi>Turba,</hi> can be driven no further, and the other fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50242:27"/>lowing with as great ſtrength, they become fenced on every ſide, with ſuch mighty preſſures, that they fill the whole lower Region, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in a manner keep off the whole body of ſuperior Air from any gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, till at laſt it is diſcharged in ſo dreadful a manner, with ſuch ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing diſploſions. And thus theſe Tempeſts by a ſmall inclination at their firſt riſings may be carried a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſtance from their local originals, and their skirts may chance to make ſo great an alteration in the weight of the Air, that they may be expected there, if not carefully obſerved, and ſo in leſſer Storms, and alſo in ſhowery Seaſons of temperate Countries, the weight of the Air will ſometimes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in this manner, when no Rain can come within eight or ten miles of the place, but if theſe Tempeſts in their perpendicular aſcenſions are equally dilated on every ſide, they are in a little time diſcharged very near the place of their firſt productions, with more or leſs violence, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the plenty of the Matter and diſpoſition of the neighbouring Air.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:50242:27"/>
               <p>Thus all theſe Tempeſts are eaſily foretold, for if in two, three, or four hours time the weight of the Air de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes 20, 30, 40, or 50 parts, we may be certain ſome of theſe ſorts of weather will follow, tho ſometimes the Winds will blow when the weight of the Air increaſes 10, 15 or 20 parts in ſix, eight or ten hours, but then it muſt decreaſe leiſurely before, and a little rain before it riſe. The ſeveral ſorts of Tempeſts may be diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the particular parts of the variation the decreaſe is made from, with reſpect to the Country and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet if it begins about 2015, and decreaſes to 1980 or leſs, it will Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der tho in Winter; if it begins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 2010, and reſt about 1970, it will be only Winds with very little Rain, but ſuch Winds as very ſeldom hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. We had an example on the ſixth of <hi>February</hi> 1698/9, at 10 over night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, a Cylinder of Air weighed 2011, the ſame morning at 7 it weighed 1991, at 10 in the forenoon it weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but 1965, which was 36 parts in three hours time, and 20 the night before, which were 56 in all, in twelve
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50242:28"/>hours time. It reſted at 1965, till a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout nine the next morning, at two afternoon it weighed 1970, and at night it weighed 2011 again, at 7 the next morning, which was the eighth, it weighed 2022. How ſtrong and tempeſtuous a wind we had at that time, not (I ſuppoſe) be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, few Houſes eſcaping its fury, and many Houſes and Barns blown quit down; and many thouſands of Elms in the Kingdom, and ſeveral Oakes, one near <hi>Hamſted</hi> 5 miles from <hi>London,</hi> twiſted like a Withe, of great Bigneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:50242:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>What Froſt and Thunder is? A conjecture at their Cauſes ond Production.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat I have to ſay upon theſe two difficult Subjects, is chiefly from Experiments and Notions that have reciprocally directed one another in ſome further and more eaſie ways of their productions, by the uſe of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, yet am not arrived beyond conjectures, but hope they will eluci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date theſe things to a further diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the very truth it ſelf. Froſt and Thunder then, I believe, are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by ſuch means as have been formerly maintained, the firſt from nitrous Saline particles diſperſed in the Air, and was only thought to be the laſt effect or production of Cold, and the other from Nitro-Sulphureous par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles in the ſame manner diſperſed, but then collected, and afterwards by ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50242:29"/>hard or difficult means ſet on fire in the midſt of ſo much Water. But Thunder I ſuppoſe may be much eaſier produced from a collection of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Rays, by a particular diſpoſition of the Effiuvious Vapours or Clouds, and Froſt by a privation of thoſe and other Calorifick Corpuſcules, which create a certain ſtifneſs, from a contrary ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and want of motion. But firſt of Thunder, our Atmoſpherical Efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via having no other original than the Terraqueous Globe and its productions, how plentifully ſoever they are ſent from the burning Mountains, Grottos and Vulcanos in <hi>Japan, China, Suma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra, Fez, Fogo, Sicily,</hi> the <hi>Alps, Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fornia, New Spain,</hi> or other places, (ſome of which are ſaid to caſt their Aſhes two hundred Miles about) either of Niter, Sulphur, Bitumine or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſimple or compounded combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter from any other parts all of the Earth or Sea; they are all too much mixed with the Aqueous Particles that accompany them or the Clouds they compoſe, to be ſet on fire in the Air, or to Thunder there, any other ways than with their Echos or Winds they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50242:29"/>produce, they may indeed thunder in theſe Vulcanos under the Earth or Water, ſhake and tear it in a terrible manner, and produce many fiery erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from ſuch places, but can never be re-inkindled in the Air, or any other diſtant places from their local originals, for if theſe Effluvia of Niter and Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur be diſtilled or ſublimed from theſe places, with never ſo great a fire, the firſt will be liquified with its own Phlegm (after the manner of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtillations) and the other by theſe, and other humid vapours in the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Clouds or Air, and ſo can never be ſet on fire after they are raiſed from their Concrets, for Thunder in the Air, I believe, is never without a Cloud and ſome Rain, nor can the ſpirits of Niter, Sulphur, Salt, Vitriol, Aquafortis or Regis, produced by theſe or any other diſtillations, being any ways mixed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with themſelves or any other things, be brought to any more than a heating Bullition, and not to an actual fire; and if we ſhould ſuppoſe the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſphere to conſiſt of two third parts of Niter and Sulphur in ſubſtance (when it is impoſſible there ſhould be one, in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50242:30"/>proportion to the other parts of the world) and to be driven never ſo cloſe by Winds and Compreſſions, the other third part will prevent the Ignition of the reſt, which is eaſily experienced by taking Niter, Sulphur, and Water of each alike in a Crucible, that will hold two or three times as much, well luted, and ſet it on a gentle; fire at firſt, the Crucible may be very red without any fire breaking out, and if then a vent be made through the Lute, to let it boyl over, which it will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately do into the fire, yet it will not kindle till the water is evaporated. We have another common Experiment in the tryal of Spirits of Wine, with Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, the moſt inflammable of any thing we know, by taking the Spirits of Wine in a Spoon, with ſome Corns of Gunpowder at the bottom, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it on fire, if there be but a little Phlegm in the Spirits, the Gunpowder will be left almoſt dry at the bottom, yet not fired, tho ſurrounded with the fire, and kept ſtirring all the while. Thus it ſeems almoſt impoſſible Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightning ſhould be produced from any thing of Niter or Sulphur, or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50242:30"/>any Terrene Effluvia without ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſiſtance, but rather from a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cave Collection of the <hi>Promethean</hi> Fire, by ſeveral Nebulous Conical Profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, which cannot be when the Air thickens by degrees for continual Rains, for then the Sun Beams are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mixed with the Effluvia, only ſome few excluded; and the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere being of one conſiſtency, there can be no ſuch diſturbance but when it is ſomewhat ſtill, and in a little dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh time and place, when the Effluvia are ſent up by more plentiful ſtreams from ſome particular places, and fewer from others, by which, if thoſe ſtreams receive a circumjacent preſſure, by their propulſions through the Effluvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Air, or be but kept from dilating, they will naturally terminate in Cones, but whether Conical or Cylindrical, thoſe neareſt the Earth will be moſt united, and thereby form the Solar Rays into erect or inclining Conical figures amongſt the Clouds, which by the Atmoſpherical Eddies and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, that are then very deep, both Fire and Water becomes more and more compreſſed, and cannot be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50242:31"/>very far before they are diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſome indirect Coruſcations, which they may gain by that motion, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in collateral or inclining one, which they may be brought to in the ſame manner, ſo that whenever the Effluvious Vapours receive or acquire, ſuch a diſpoſition, with ſufficient depth and denſity, it may Thunder tho in Winter; and for further confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, if we take an ordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cave-Glaſs, and concenturate the Sun Beams, but upon a Baſon of Water, they will quickly put it into a Bullition, and if kept ſteady upon the ſame place for ſome time, they will at laſt give it the ſame motion and ſound of Thunder, with that in the Clouds; but if with a onveniently ſhap'd and ſized Glaſs, like a Boult-head, with a long neck, being exactly placed and filled with fair water, and with a good Concave-glaſs, the Sun Beams be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centurated upon that ſolid body of Water in the other Glaſs, with care to heat it leiſurely, that the fire may not crack the Glaſs, till throughly warm, and then kept ſteady upon the ſame place as before, theſe Igneous Corpuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50242:31"/>will not only bring that water to the ſame Thundring Bullitions with that in the Clouds by the various im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive motions of its riſing and falling, but theſe very Beams by thoſe impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions will variouſly penetrate both glaſs and water in diverſe linghtning flaſhes. Thus we have no occaſion to fill the Air with ſo much Niter and Sulphur to ſave the Phaenomenon of Thunder and Lightning, but it will be ſufficient to have it ſeaſoned like other products, then for the Lightnings coming downwards, either right, ſide ways, or inclining, and as it was thought contrary to the nature of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fire, whoſe flame was alſo thought would go no other ways but upwards, till by melting Niter in ſome Iron or other Sulphureous Veſſels, that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and penetrating Salt by that heat mixing with the imbibed Oyl or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetred Sulphur, as ſoon as it has ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a compleat red body of fire (I ſay a body of fire) whoſe Atoms ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame paſſages, can as well go back, as they came in, and theſe Saline Particles can now (we ſee) by the help of that Oyl or Sulphur accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50242:32"/>them with natural Coruſcations, for Niter being made a body of fire that conſiſts of ſuch ſubtile or rather ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituous parts, to what part ſoever the Oyl or Sulphur, or any other combuſtible matter is contiguous, from thence the flaſhes muſt proceed (there being nothing to hinder) as well downwards, inclining or ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways as right up, and ſo from any other body of fire, that is not fuel, as well as Niter, for Niter is no ways inflammable of its ſelf, which may ſoon be proved in a Crucible at any time, but it is impoſſible the flame of any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtable matter alone, however diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhould go any other ways than up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards (except the Air incline it other ways, becauſe the Terrene Propulſions are made that ways, and increaſed by the heat if near, and moſt ſuch things growing liquid, by inverſion, and that weight are extinguiſhed, but yet it is as unlikely if not impoſſible that any fiery flaſhes ſhould be produced from any Terrene Concrete to be continued to half that ſtrength and diſtance that Lightning is known to be of, nor can they by any means be brought to a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50242:32"/>true reſemblance, not thoſe of Niter and Sulphur, to them of Lightning, whoſe Rays being univerſally defu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, are eaſily collected, and may be compreſſed a thouſand times more than a little Air in a wind Gun, to ſolve the Phaenomena of many other Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but the hardeſt of all is, that it is often times known to Hail with Thunder and Lightning, how theſe Clouds that contain ſo much fire, ſhould yet freeze the water is very ſtrange, that it cannot in thundring weather well be thought to freeze in falling, as was formerly aſſerted, but rather that in warm ſeaſons, as ſome places become dry, ſo the moiſt ones ſend up more plentiful Effluvia, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by theſe plentiful Effluvia become li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to ſuch places, and more Jejune Effluvia to the dry ones, which being augmented to a ſufficient depth and denſity, they will both exclude, and collect the Solar Rays at the ſame time, the more powerfully by this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and their contrary qualities; and ſo may Hail and Thunder at the ſame time, tho in hot weather, this alſo is the reaſon why commonly the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50242:33"/>Spring time (and not in Summer) is more windy and ſtormy than any other Seaſon, and from hence another of more wet in Autumn, but will be too much for this ſhort account, tho it would further elucidate the matter, and give an explication to that of Froſt, which I ſhall now endeavour to evince by theſe Experiments.</p>
               <p>Froſt then being only an ultimate (but may be not the moſt ultimate) effect of Cold, is produced by greater or leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer degrees of that, and that not by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſubject of Inhaeſion, but by a priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of heat, Paucity of Calorifick Corpuſcles, and want of motion, or leſſer agitation, and contrary tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: Froſt therefore being only an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or product of Cold, is either more or leſs intenſe, according to the degrees of its Cauſe, and cold more or leſs freezing according to the privation of heat, and Paucity of Calorifick Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcles. What this heat is, and from whence theſe Corpuſcles come, muſt therefore be conſidered; the heat is of two ſorts, either Terrene, or from the Heavens; the firſt from ſeveral Vulca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, internal Bullitions, and ferment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50242:33"/>Emotions, all which are ſubject to intermiſſions, and obſtructions, becauſe they proceed from no univerſal matter, or cauſe, and ſeveral ſubſidences may both obſtruct, and extinguiſh them; the other from the Heavens cannot be thus extinguiſhed, but may be ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ways hindered or obſtructed by Hills or Mountains, and ſeveral diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of the Effluvious Vapours, or may be carried off ſome other way by the winds or particular currents of Air, or by the Central motion of the Sun to parts of leſs heat, or not extended far enough for the Latitude of the place, theſe obſtructions or privations of heat makes a Chaſm between theſe and thoſe incorporated in the parts of all natural Bodies, the incorporated particles (as all heat and fire do) ſoon fade and die, which for want of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, as ſoon leave all the external parts, eſpecially leſs active, more extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and therefore more ſtiff, more poroſe, and more bulky, which are the common qualificatiens of Froſt, and from theſe all the other may be eaſily deduced.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:50242:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>That there never is no ſettled Froſt to hold, when the Air continues to weigh</hi> 2020 <hi>or more, nor never no Thunder when it weighs but</hi> 1980, <hi>or leſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving now given ſome account what Froſt and Thunder is, tho my Experiments have not enabled me to obſerve all the circumſtances relating to the Title of this Chapter, we hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had no great Froſts or Thunders ſince I have been Maſter of it, yet by reaſon of many other Meteorologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Concurrencies in the alterations of the weather, which I have often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced, that are in ſome ſort like a Magnetick Clinatory, being plainly applied, ſhew only South and North, yet by theſe we are alſo ſhewn Eaſt and Weſt, and all the other points without removing it to them Plains, ſo I hope by the Experiments I have
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50242:34"/>made in other alterations, and ſome few I have made in theſe, to tell the truth of both without ſtaying any longer for theſe ſorts of weather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides being but the reverſe of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter, as to the effects upon the Barometer, it will the more eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then there can be no Froſt to hold, when the Air continues to weigh 2020 or more, yet no ſettled fair weather (except Froſt) if it weighs 10 or 15 parts leſs, and yet I believe there have been no laſting Froſts yet known, but in fair weather, how Froſt then which is only an effect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he privation of heat ſhould continue when there is nothing that appears <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o hinder the Sun Beams, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here ſhould be no ſuch froſty wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her when the Atmoſphere continues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be crowded with the thickeſt Clouds of Rain, Hail, Snow, Miſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r other Vapours, which ſeems whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to obſtruct, them is ſomewhat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>range, till we conſider that all theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffluvia, whether of Rain, Hail, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>now, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are the products of ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bterraneal Bullitions, or other fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50242:35"/>or of the Sun's reverbora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but let it be from which of them it will, the ſame effects will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, for that Heat or Motion that raiſes them, or the Calorifick Corpuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles conjoyned, do we ſee keep them all fluid beneath, therefore we may be ſure there muſt much more heat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained amongſt thoſe particles that are near a thouſand times more denſe than thoſe of Air, to maintain their fluidity, and keep them from freezing, thus it is almoſt impoſſible we ſhould have any Froſt on Earth, when we have ſuch a fuming Sea about us (yet we oftentimes feel it more Cold in ſuch ſorts of weather than in clear and froſty Seaſons, becauſe our corporeal Emanations can eaſier keep of a lighter than a heavier Medium or Preſſure, therefore our Senſories can make no true diſtinctions of the degrees of Cold) but as ſoon as ever the Rain or Snow is over, it will immediately Freeze, but can never hold when the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere is thus filled, for the former reaſons, but when the Air weighs 2005, 10, 12 or 15, if the Latitude of the place, diſpoſition of the Country, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50242:35"/>Seaſon of the Year be proper, it will certainly freeze, yet not at the extreami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Sun Beams, or Earths ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face firſt, for thoſe Igneous Atoms in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated there, by their own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and ſome few emotions will prevent that, and make the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings ſo far in the Air, as thoſe emotions reach from the earth, which gradually as theſe emotions, ceaſe and dye for want of renovations, is extended more and more down, till the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſurface of the earth it ſelf is thus deprived and frozen, many of which frozen particles being conſtantly emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, do as well fill the Atmoſphere as other Vapours, ſo that the Air can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver weigh 2020 if the froſt continues, but leſs and leſs by the froſty emiſſions filling the Atmoſphere, for if it weighs 2020, the Sun Beams will come unob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed upon us, and give no place to any ſuch thing, which they can never do near the Poles, or in other cold Countries, theſe are the Reaſons that the Quickſilver in the Common Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters in ſome places is quit loſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Regiſter Plate, and in others far above it, which the Portable one diſcovers before hand.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:50242:36"/>
               <p>Then for Thunder, if it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the ways related in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter, we may be almoſt ſure when the Air weighs but 1980, the Atmoſphere will be too much filled with the Effluvious Vapours, and much more diſpoſed for continual Rains (which will too much wet the Fulminous Particles) then for Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or Storms, except <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſhould ſend a Meſſenger amongſt them, for tho Thunder (I ſuppoſe) is not known to be without Rain, yet it is not known neither I believe in continual Rains, beſides in Summer Seaſons and warm weather, the Air does for the moſt part weigh the more, and not often times leſs, not long together, for if it ſhould I am ſure the weather would be very unnatural, as well as unſeaſonable to the Summers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts, and might rather be called Winter than Summer; but when it weighs 2014, 2020, 25, 30, or 40, and the weight decreaſes 15, 20, 25 or 30 parts in 12 or 24 hours, it will be ſure to Thunder more or leſs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the parts of variation it has decreaſed, and the time it was made in,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50242:36"/>for then the Sun Beams being more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant are more powerful, and by their diſpoſitions in the former Chapter are more eaſily collected, and thereby greater Thunders and Lightnings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, ſo that when ever the weight of the Air alters, tho never ſo much, if it did not weigh above 1980 before the alteration began, we may be ſure there will be no Thunder, but only tempeſtuous Winds, and Rains, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther here nor in no other parts of the world, for in cold Countries it does not often weigh a great deal more, nor in hot ones not often a great deal lefs, which is eaſily proved without go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into them places, with ſeveral years continuance to make the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and will without doubt be of further uſe in many other reſpects, if improved and applied as it may be to ſeveral other natural diſcoveries; and by abſtractions, in time, to the very Center of Beings, the Almighty, Grand and Catholick Efficient, that is in and through all things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:50242:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>That tho a Cylinder of Air weighs much leſs in wet or windyweather, than it does in dry weather, yet in a ſettled froſt, tho the Air appears never ſo clear and dry, it weighs much lighter than at any other time.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis ſeeming Paradox, and may be that about weighing the winds would both of them been much more ſtrange, as well as hard and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to clear without this Inſtrument, which is ſo eaſie to carry whereever we go, and as eaſie at all times and places to weigh the Air with, That if the Honourable Eſquire <hi>Boyle</hi> had been ſo happy, he might have known the reaſon why the Air was ſo thick in <hi>Nova Zembla,</hi> that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Clock would not go without the charge he was willing to give to know the weight of his Aeolipile full of that Air in the midſt of Winter, in his <hi>Phyſico-motion:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50242:37"/>Exper. pag.</hi> 148. And in his <hi>Hiſt. of Cold pag.</hi> 91. he has many ſuggeſtions about the ſame Clock, and Captain <hi>James</hi>'s Clock, and Watch that win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered at <hi>Charleton,</hi> and at laſt ſays they are but conjectures) for by this it is eaſier to make a hundred Experiments in weighing the Air, than one either with an Aeolipile, or the Air Pump, and thus in time to diſcover a great many more particulars, hard and unthought of qualifications that may be would never have been known other ways, for if according to the Rules, or Laws of Hydroſtaticks and Philoſophy, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral qualifications of Liquids are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by their Gravity, this that both weighs and meaſures at the ſame time muſt needs diſcover many more in all natural bodies, as well as this of Air, and has already diſcovered ſome much more ſubtile than the common Air, and will eaſily go where that cannot, and may be produced in one weeks time, what this diſcovery may lead to I know not, but am ſure that which diſcovered it is capable of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:50242:38"/>
               <p>That the Air weighs leſs in wet or windy weather, than in dry weather our Experiments proves, and have told the reaſons in the Second and fifth Chapters but how it ſhould weigh leſs in hard froſty weather, which ſeems to be more dry, is yet to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into, for that cannot be from a greater plenty of the Effluvious Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, becauſe by this they are now all impriſoned (in a manner) within the Earths ſurface, nor from an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary agitation of the Air with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Winds, becauſe there is nothing to put it into ſuch a motion when the Air is ſo clear. But becauſe thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt inconceiveable minute Igneous Particles that are ſo eaſie collected in a Concave Glaſs, and may be conſtitute the whole Aether, and diſperſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves throughout all the Terraqueous Effluvia are by ſeveral cauſes or obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions moſtly hindred, the other grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Languid fade and die in the ſame manner as the Atoms of our common Culinary Fires do, and want a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual ſupply like them, with other ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedanums to maintain thoſe curious agitations of the Atmoſphere, that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50242:38"/>keep it from Congelation, theſe being wanting the Effluvious Vapours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more and more ſtiff, unactive, cold, or frigid, and at laſt to a perfect Gelicidation, this continuing makes the whole Hemiſpherical part of the Atmoſphere like one Gelicidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, that with longer time grows thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and harder, reaching higher and higher, and ſo more and more keeps off the Airs Gravitation which it can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly penitrate, becauſe Ice is much more inpenetrable than the greateſt winds or Clouds of Rain, Hail, Snow, or other Vapours, whereby a Cylinder of Air muſt weigh much leſs in a long and ſetled Froſt than at any other time, and yet the Air for the moſt part much more clear there in the hoteſt or dryeſt ſeaſons, (for they ſometimes want a good rain to clear it) it being eaſier to ſee through the ſtraight particles of Ice, than the curvid ones of miſts and other Vapours, and thus places at a further diſtance may be much more eaſily ſeen, and the Stars more numerous, and yet the refraction very much greater by this Glaciation, all which Captain <hi>James</hi> relates in his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50242:39"/>to the Iſlands of <hi>Charleton,</hi> that on the thirtieth and thirty firſt of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> he ſaw two third parts more Stars than ever he had ſeen before, <hi>pag.</hi> 62, and the Cloud in <hi>Cancer</hi> full of ſmall Stars, and the Sun to riſe twenty mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes before it ſhould, and ſet ſo much later, by reaſon of this Glaciating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraction <hi>pag.</hi> 64. and yet not more North than we in <hi>England,</hi> in the Latitude of 52°, or little more, <hi>pag.</hi> 46. But the <hi>Hollanders</hi> at <hi>Nova Zem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bla</hi> ſaw the Sun 14 days ſooner than he ſhould have appeared, by this mighty refraction; this made the Air ſo clear, yet ſo thick (or rather ſtiff) as Eſquire <hi>Boyle</hi> calls it, that the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> Clock would not go at <hi>Nova Zembla,</hi> nor Captain <hi>James</hi> Clock nor Watch at the Iſland of <hi>Charleton,</hi> thus theſe Herculian Contradictions are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, and the uſefulneſs of this Inſtrument further manifeſted, tho never at the Iſland of <hi>Charlton, Nova Zembla,</hi> or <hi>Green-Land</hi> to weigh the Air in thoſe places, where an Aeoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pile of Air in the midſt of Winter hardly weighs more than this of ours in clear weather, and the midſt of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50242:39"/>Summer, for I dare undertaken to gueſs the exact weight of an Aeolipile of Air with this Barometer in any ſort of Weather, Place or Time, tho according to the Experiments in the Second Chapter an Aeolipile of Air ſometimes weighs leſt when a Cylinder of Air weighs heavieſt, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times otherways. I ſay ſometimes, for if it were always, that would as well foretell the alterations of weather as the Barometer, and thus alſo, beſides it is eaſie to prove that Igneous Atoms as well as other Particles have their proper mediums of Retention as well as Incorporation, and our Atmoſpheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Air being ſo thin a fluid, it can hold them but a little while, tho ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much incorporated, they having ſo great a liberty do as ſwiftly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue it, and as quickly arrive at the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of their Extenſions and Extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, therefore it cannot retain them, except it would alſo prevent their Extentions, but if the Atmoſphere be conſtantly filled with a great plenty of Effluvious Vapours, tho the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methean</hi> Fire be wanting, that which remains and Reverberates with the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50242:40"/>Terraqueous Emotions conſtantly aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting (and being in a thicker medium, tho there be a leſs degree of heat in appearance, yet it will be longer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained) will keep it from freezing, all which is further demonſtrable from all other liquids, if heated the thicker they are the longer they keep hot, or whether actually heated or not, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Thermometer will diſcover River or Pond-water in Winter time, (and ſometimes in a warmer Seaſon) to be hoter than the Air; and Sea or Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water to be warmer than thoſe, and Oyl of Tartar or Vitriol hoter than the Salt-water; and Quickſilver the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt liquid we know, which all the world look upon to be very cold, to be warmer than any of them, and ſo many others likewiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:50242:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Whether the planetary Beams or influences can cauſe an alteration of weather, to be foretold by them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat ſome Aſtrologers have told us about the alterations of the weather from the Planets, is no ways ſatisfactory, and very ſtrange it ſhould be continued down to theſe times, that ſome of our Vertuoſi have not told us ſomething about that as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther natural diſcoveries, that we might be no longer impoſed upon, by telling us the ſeveral ſorts of winds and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are appropriated to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Planets, but have told us neither Reaſon nor Cauſe of this Appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and others that the ſeveral Planets are Authors of theſe ſorts of winds and weather: and another that has writ only of the Weather tells us the Seven viſible Planets in the Skies have their Correſpondent ones, in the Air, and in the Bowels of the Earth,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50242:41"/>that are night and day at work in making thoſe forts of weather for us, and thereby undertakes to tell the cauſe of all the vulgar Prognoſticators errors, and the true way of judging the weather, with as much truth as the reſt: For indeed it is impoſſible that either Winds, Rain, or fair wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Froſt, Snow, or Thunder ſhould proceed from the Planets, they being compoſed of no ſuch matters, nor are they intelligent to effect it, yet it muſt be acknowledged that the Sun and Moon, and the reſt of the Planets, and other Stars have their particular Rays of Light (but whether theſe Rays of Light are Beams of fire or not, and differ only in quantity, and not in quality, as their different lights appear, and from whence they have their lights, whether inate or not, will be too much for this ſhort account) and that thoſe from the Sun (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) at any time of the year (but too apparent to be queſtioned in Summer time) are of ſufficient power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe ſeveral Vapours, Miſts and Clouds raiſed from our Terraqueous Globe, for 'tis the Earth, and not the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50242:41"/>Sun, Moon, or Stars that is the firſt Mother of Meteors, 'tis the Terrene Emotions with ſome new modificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that gives birth to them all, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the firſt, ſecond, and third Chapters, and not the Planers conjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in watery Signs, where may be they placed the watery Windows of Heaven, ſpoken of in the ſeventh of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that makes their <hi>Apertio Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum,</hi> or opening the Gates of Heaven, and thoſe that rained Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone on <hi>Sodom</hi> in fiery Signs, and others in Airy ones, but we never heard what from earthly ſigns, therefore as none of theſe ſorts of weather can proceed from the Planets, ſo neither can they from any of the Signs, nor the Planets con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned in them, but the Effluvia being raiſed in the preceeding manner are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determined Preciſely, both to time and place, yet by ſeveral Eruptions, Propul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Rarefactions, Compreſſions, and Reſilitions they may receive, or meet with as well in their firſt aſcenſions as afterwards, they may be driven, ſpread and diſcharged to and in ſeveral di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant places, without any other aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but theſe chiefly happen in the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50242:42"/>Torrid Zone, or in ſome Hilly or Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainous Countries, or near ſome Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canos, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by Paroxyſms, and not often in more open and plain Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries or Temperate Climates, and are conſtant no where, whereby the Efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via are ſometimes in the firſt ſort of places left, and at moſt times in other places, to the diſpoſal of the Beams or Influences of the Heavens, which I believe may be evinced, of ſufficient power to alter and diſperſe them: Firſt of the Sun Beams, which in moſt Countries are known every day they appear, but a few hours to diſperſe all foggy Miſts and Vapours, and turn a dark Cloudy morning into a clear and fair Day, not by any occult property, but by a manifeſt one, as all other heat in Boyling, Diſtilling, or other Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction does: and ſo for winds, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral or Trade Winds, are always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Courſe of the Sun or Earth, as far as theſe Beams and the inferiour Tract is conformable or proper, ſome degrees beyond the whole breadth of the Zodiack on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, they conſtantly propelling all humid Vapours and Air before them,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50242:42"/>and ſo likewiſe the Monſoons, which Sir <hi>Thomas Herbert</hi> in his Travels, ſays, begin exactly at the Sun's entrance into a Sign of the Zodiack, and blow half a year conſtantly that way, till the Sun enter into the oppoſite De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and then they blow in the ſame manner the other way. Captain <hi>Swanly</hi> ſays, the Monſoons raigns five months on one ſide of the Compaſs, and five months on the other, and that there are two months in which they change, are variable (or break up, as ſome term theſe alterations) in <hi>March</hi> and <hi>September,</hi> when the Sun croſſes the Line, and as long as the Sun is on the north ſide of the Aequator, to the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pique of Cancer, the winds are to the northward, and veery more northerly according to the courſe of the months, and when on the South ſide of the AE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial, the winds blow from thence in the ſame manner, and thus alſo there is half a year of fair Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoons, and half a year of Rainy and fowl Monſoons, and that the fair Monſoons blow off the Shoars, and the Rainy Monſoons on the Shoars, and that near all Lands, between the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50242:43"/>Tropicks, Eaſtwards of <hi>Cape-Bon-Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance</hi> in the rainy Monſcons there happen ſome fair intervals, but in the dry Monſoons ſeldom any rain, and to this purpoſe many other relations might be as eaſily tranſeribed, but that the certain knowledge and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of all our own, and other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Seamen to thoſe places make it needleſs, thus we ſee the Beams in thoſe neighbouring Regions are ſo plentiful and turgid, that they drive all before them in winds, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant dry weather, if of the Land ſide, and with almoſt continual rains, if from the Sea, thus alſo theſe tumultuous and unequal crowds of Effluvia make that inequality of heat and cold that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſta</hi> relates, and complains of in the burning Zone, where he had the Sun for Zenith and expected to be ſcorched with heat, he was forced to go into the Sun-ſhine for warmth, and that he ſaw Snow, Hail and frozen water on the tops of Mountains, and the cold ſo bitter that all the Graſs was withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and Men and Beaſts benumed that paſſed that way, <hi>pag.</hi> 101 and 109: and this North and South, wind
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50242:43"/>heat and cold, wet and dry weather proceeded from the Sun's local poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, on the North or South ſide of their Zenith, or Equator, as his Rays de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline from their perpendicularity, and not from fiery, airy, watery, or earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Signs, for the Sun beams are not earthly in us, nor watery in ♉, but fiery in ♋, and always ſo powerful in the Torid Zone, that they are the chief efficients of all theſe ſorts of weather, without any aſſiſtance from the other Planets, there being hardly any room for any of their beams to crowd in.</p>
               <p>Secondly, of the beams of the Moon, theſe being from a leſſer light have not ſo many manifeſt operations as thoſe of the Sun, yet are known in ſeveral places of <hi>India,</hi> and the Torid Zone to cauſe contractures in the Bodies of thoſe that are too long expoſed to them, as well to the Natives as Strangers, tho more to the latter, and that ſeveral are made Lame, or elſe have had ſome of their Limbs contracted for ſeveral weeks, and ſome for as many months, and others to their lives end, if they happen to ſleep where the Moon ſhines upon them, which ſeveral of our Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50242:44"/>who go to thoſe places have alſo ſeen, and a friend of mine, a Relation and Merchant that Traded and Lived ſometime in the Iſland of <hi>Sunda</hi> at <hi>Achem</hi> in <hi>Sumatra,</hi> and <hi>Bantum</hi> in <hi>Java</hi> and had traveled many other parts of <hi>India,</hi> aſſured me he had ſeen ſeveral that had their Limbs contracted, and their Mouths or Necks ſo drawn aſide and twiſted by the beams of the Moon, that they were very ſurpriſing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and that he himſelf when he came firſt into thoſe parts, before he was acquainted with it, took up his Lodging after an extream hot day (according to the cuſtom of the place) in the open air, with ſlender cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where the Moons beams could fully come for good part of the night which being paſt before he waked, when he went to riſe, he found the left ſide of his neck, and up to his Ear, and the ſame Arm and Soulder (which was very much expoſed) ſo ſtiff that he was ſcarce able to ſtir himſelf, and was forced to keep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in eight or ten days to be cured, which was done by the conſtant uſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward Aromaticks of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:50242:44"/>Country for that time, and that the Country people told him the next morning, if he had acquainted them with his deſign, or had paſſed the night where they did, he would have prevented that miſchief by lodging in a place unexpoſed to the Moons Beams.</p>
               <p>The reaſons of theſe diſaſters muſt be that the beams of the Moon like thoſe of the Sun, do propel the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Effluvia before them, but having no ſuch heat as they have, theſe Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluvia thus driven, enter the Pores of the Body in the expoſed parts with a contrary tendency, and much leſs agitated than the Animal Spirits and Humours, and thereby cool and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their natural motions, and circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, theſe Nutricious Spirits and Juices being thus hindred, a paucid Lympha ſupplies (which has no ſuch motion) and thereby Tumefies, Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cts and hinders the proper motion of the part it poſſeſſes, which the heat of the body ſoon exſiccates (may be as it comes), and ſo confirms it: and as theſe people ſay, it is only the beams of the Moon, ſo neither can we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50242:45"/>it ſhould be any thing elſe, for it ſhould proceed from the Wind or cold Damps, then it might be as well when the Moon did not ſhine upon them, or in ſome other parts than thoſe on which it did ſhine, which is not known, and when they do take up their lodging in the open air we cannot ſuppoſe neither that the Wind ſhould be concentred upon them through any crack or hole: beſides be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the open air, the continual Streams or Effiuvia of their own bodies both warm and keep off the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing air from every part, equal to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſtrength of their motions, and ſo ſecures them in all places that are but moderately calm and ſtill. Then for the Beams of the other Planets and Stars, there is none can ſay they are refracted, either by the Aether, Air, or Atmoſphere, but that they paſs directly down upon us, and ſo penetrate every part of all theſe in their deſcenſions, as we ſee and know their light is ſent down thus far; theſe beams therefore having ſo great a power, (notwithſtanding the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Diurnal Circumgyration of the Earth or Heavens) to continue their
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:50242:45"/>direct courſes hither, muſt needs move, alter and impell the Effluvious Air before them (but yet no other ways than according to their direct poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) and ſo may either bring or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from us miſty, rainy or ſnowy Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, or otherways may put the Air into a direct or contrary motion, and ſo produce Winds, Storms, Tempeſts, Thunders, Hurricanes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which may thus be foretold at any time, and from what quarter the Wind will blow, with as much certainty as their Motions, and Poſitions are known, and by this means there will be (or rather is) a new account of their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects, according to the Lines and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles they make at the earth, and not amongſt themſelves, nor from fiery, airy, watery, or earthly ſigns, for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe can have any reſpect to us, of which this Barometer has given a Diagram, that by taking the Planets places from an Ephemeris to their true places in that, all the alterations of weather, and winds from their Quarters may be foretold at any time.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:50242:46"/>
               <p>And further tho not ſo proper here, theſe beams that are able to penetrate, move and alter the air, which we can no ways ſubſiſt, nor live one hour without, are as capable to penetrate our bodies as that (which we know the beams of the Sun does, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and move and alter our ſpirits, and ſo the ſpirits of all other bodies which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be leſs ſubject to theſe motions and alterations than ours are, and if our ſpirits and the ſpirits of all other bodies may be moved and altered by theſe beams, then theſe ſpirits being the immediate cauſes, and only princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Life, Power, Vertue, Force and Strength, it will be impoſſible they ſhould be altred and changed, and no alterations made in the bodies them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; therefore a leſs limit of the power of theſe beams cannot be ſet, than what muſt at length terminate as well in the bodies themſelves. All which I hope to demonſtrate further by infalliable proofs, if life and leiſure ſerve, in a Treatiſe by it ſelf, what theſe Beams and Motions are, that they have power to cauſe all the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of winds and weather we are
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50242:46"/>acquainted with, and all other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon alterations in our and other Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Bodies and Spirits, by the Lines and Angles they make at the Earth, and not by their beholding one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by Sextile, Quartile, Trine or Oppoſition, which may ſerve till then, for tho it be the firſt, yet I believe the moſt that ever was publiſhed before in this way, and queſtion not but future Obſervations will confirm (not the Names and Motions, but) the Laws of the Stars thereby, for from hence there is a reaſon why the Planets, Poles of Poſitions, and the Diviſions of the Heavens are taken according to the Latitude of the Place, in an Oblique Sphere, and many other things as perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, butreferred till then.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:50242:47"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>That it is impoſſible by any Hygroſcope, Thermometer or other Invention to know the true ſtate of the Air.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving now given a ſhort account of the preceding Heads, it will be convenient to ſay ſomething of the common Inſtruments that are uſed to foretell the alterations of weather by; or that the alterations of the Air are uſed to have an influence upon; and ſuch are of three ſorts. Firſt ſuch as imbibe the Effluvious Air, and are Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Hygroſcopes. Secondly, ſuch as have a parcel of Air included with ting'd Spirits and ſealed up in Cylindrical Glaſſes, and are Callid Thermometers: or thirdly, ſuch as contain ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituous or other liquid in a Cylindri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal pipe of Glaſs, clos'd at one end, and open at the other, and inverted into an open Vial or Ciſtern of the ſame
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:50242:47"/>liquor, expoſed to the open Air, and are Callid Thermoſcopes or Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Hygroſcopes are of ſeveral ſorts, but the moſt Fam'd one is that of a wild Oat-beard, deſcribed in Mr <hi>Hookes</hi> Mirrographia, <hi>page</hi> 147, others are made of Sheeps Gutts or Fiddle-ſtrings, Pieces of Leather, Ropes, Cords, Sponge, Wool, Paper or Deal-ſhavings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and may be made of any other thing that will imbi be the humid Air, or that the Air can eaſily penetrate, as Willow, Sallow, Ozier, Alder, and other ſoft woods.</p>
               <p>That of an Oat-beard turns and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns in dry and moiſt weather, and is fitted with an Index that points to all the variations; Sheeps-guts, Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-ſtrings, Pieces of Leather, Ropes and other Cords are faſtened againſt ſome Wall, Board or Timber, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended either Horizontally or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicularly, and then a convenient weight hung on the middle or other end will riſe and fall in wet and dry weather.</p>
               <p>Sponge, Wooll, Paper, or Deal-ſhavings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are tyed together with
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50242:48"/>ſome ſtring, or in a thin Silk or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Caſe, or Bag, in a round or oval form or balance, with Scales and Weights, which will be heavier or lighter in wet or dry weather.</p>
               <p>The imperfections of all which are eaſily ſeen, firſt, in reſpect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their adjuſtings; and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in reſpect of the alterations of the Air, in reſpect of themſelves, the Oat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beards will in a little time grow much more ſtiff, hard, cloſe, and brittle, and inſtead of two, three, or four times turning about will not turn once, and not long before it will not move at all, which it gradually comes to as it grows more and more Ramalious, or ſare and Dead, for which reaſon alſo there can be no certain adjuſting of that, for by the time it can be adjuſted at firſt, the Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of its parts will be ſo much altered in relation to its motion, that it will want a new adjuſtion, and ſo Sheeps-gutts, Fiddle-ſtrings, Pieces of Leather, Ropes, or other Cords, do all alter in the ſame manner; nor can Sponge, Wooll, Paper, or Deal-ſhavings, or any other ſuch thing? be preſerved or any ways ſecured from the ſame inconvenience?
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50242:48"/>but if they could, it would yet be impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they ſhould ſhew any alteration of weather with any manner of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, for as they only imbibe, and are receptacles of the ſubtile Humid Vapours, that ſometimes fill the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Regions before it rains, ſo they can ſhew no other alterations, but what they make in their coming and going, which are ſometimes much more in Miſts after it has rained, or when there is no rain follows, or upon the going a way of a Froſt, or melting of a Snow, than at coming of the greateſt rains, and ſo on the contrary, when theſe Vapours cannot come ſo low in froſty or windy weather, they will ſhew no alteration till after the rain is come, and Snow ſeldom makes any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations in them, except it melts as it falls: And in Summer time and dry Seaſons, it is ſo alſo, no alteration till the rain is coming, or that it have rained, but if a miſty morning happen, they will alter much more. Beſides, if all theſe inconveniencies could be preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they cannot well be put into a travelling Security, by reaſon of the ſeveral alterations they will be ſubject
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50242:49"/>to from the heat of the Body, Warmth, and Fires in Houſes, and the different tempers of the Air abroad.</p>
               <p>Secondly, thoſe that have a parcel of Air included with tinged Spirits, and ſealed up in Cylindrical Glaſſes, theſe for diſtinction are called Hermetick Thermometers, and of a later inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thereby thought by ſome to exceed all other diſcoveries for heat and cold, but are not pretended, nor intended, to ſhew any thing elſe, which by the natural Expanſion and Contraction of the included Air with heat, and cold, gives way for the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and falling of the Spirits, and have no manner of tendency for wet and dry, and therefore of very ſmall uſe or ſervice; for we know the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſometimes very cold, yet fair and dry, and ſometimes as cold when it rains, ſnows, or blows, and ſometimes fair and dry in hot weather, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as wet or windy. But as the former are deficient in wet and dry, ſo are theſe in heat and cold, and it is impoſſible they ſhould ſhew any truth in what they pretend, for no body has yet told us the proportion between
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:50242:49"/>the Head and the Cylinder, nor can they make two to rife and fall alike, with the ſame Spirits, nor have they told us what is beſt to put in them, whether Spirits of Wine, Vinegar, Salt, Vitriol, Tartar or Sulphur, or Oyl of Turpentine, Amber, Wax, or Anis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or other things, beſides all liquids are expanded, and contracted with Heat and Cold, ſo apparently, that our Seamen have obſerved their Ships to draw leſs Water in Cold and Frozen Countries (tho the Water is not in thoſe places ſo Salt, therefore not naturally ſo heavy) than they do in warmer places, ſo that the Water is thicker and heavier in cold than in warmer places, and ſeaſons: and the Honourable Eſquire <hi>Boyle</hi> has obſerved it to Dilate and Contract it ſelf in the ſame day, by a Hermetick Glaſs Bub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that would ſink in Water at noon time, and riſe and ſwim night and morning. Therefore if Water will thus viſibly Dilate and Contract it ſelf in ſuch large quantities and places, it will be much more ſo in the ſlender ſtem of a Thermometer, and any ſort of volatile ſpirits, a great many times
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:50242:50"/>more than Salt or other Fountain Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and thus alſo ſome Spirits will Dilate and Contract more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which makes all theſe things the more uncertain, and no body knows how much theſe ſpirits will Dilate and Contract themſelves by Heat or Cold; yet there is a way to make a Thermometer free from all theſe exceptions, which I have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in another way: then for the other ſorts that are called Thermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that alter both with Heat and Cold, Wet and Dry, by having Air in the top of the Cylinder, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the preſſure of the air at the bottom, theſe are the greateſt confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that can be, for they ſhew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of truth but by chance, nor can any body tell when they do, or do not, for if it be cold and wet, the cold will contract the air above to make it riſe, and the wet will lighten the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpherical Cylinder to make it ſink, thus it is unpoſſible it ſhould riſe and fall at the ſame time, and ſo in hot and fair weather, the heat will dilate the air above to make it ſink, and in fair weather the Atmeſphere preſſes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:50242:50"/>the heavieſt at the bottom, to make it riſe, and thus whenever they riſe or fall no body can tell whether it be for heat or cold, wet or dry weather.</p>
               <p>Then for the Quickſilver-Glaſs, or Common Barometer, there is none that have them but know they will ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fall or ſink very conſiderably, yet no rain follow, and at other times rain if it ſink never ſo little, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſometimes it will be fair, tho it riſe, but little, and at other times very wet when it riſes conſiderably: Nor have they given us any certain rules to know when it will rain or be fair, ſo that all theſe Inſtruments are very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect and can no ways be truſted to. And thus I have told the Reaſons, and next for the Uſe of that, that will do all theſe things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:50242:51"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>The uſe of the Portable Barometer, how to weigh the Air, Meaſure its Height, and foretell all the alterations of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving now given a ſhort account of the reaſons for the uſe of this Barometer, and the inſufficiency of all others to foretell any alteration of the weather by, it will now be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to ſhew how to uſe it, to weigh the Air, Meaſure its height, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell the alterations of the weather by it. Firſt how to uſe it.</p>
               <p>Let the Barometer hang perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular in one hand, and by more o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leſs weights with the other bring i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to a true Aequilibrium or even Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, ſo have you the exact weigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of any quantity of Air you deſire, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the meaſure of its height, by the ſecond and fourteenth of the Twelfth of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clid</hi>'s
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:50242:51"/>
                  <hi>Elements of Geometry.</hi> Firſt, by the ſecond of the Twelfth thus;</p>
               <p>Circles are in the ſame Ratio, as are the Squares of their Diameters, which is thus wrought as the Square of the Standard Diameter is to the Square of the Diameter propoſed; ſo is the weight of this to the weight of that, and the bigneſs of the former, to that of the latter.</p>
               <p>Then by the fourteenth of the twelfth, that Cylinders and Cones, having the ſame Baſe, are in the ſame Ratio as are their heights, which are thus wrought, as the Baſe of the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard Cylinder or Cone, is to the Baſe of the Cylinder or Cone Propoſed, ſo are the heights of thoſe, to the heights of theſe, and the Contents of the former to thoſe of the later, thus we have not only the exact weight of any parcel or quantity of Air at any time, but the meaſure of its Height at all times, and in all places.</p>
               <p>And thus alſo we may weigh any other liquid in its Fountain, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure its Depth: If we deſire only its weight, we need only to put in the Inſtrument to balance any particular
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:50242:52"/>quantity, ſo we have the exact weight by meaſure, but if to meaſure the Depth as well, it muſt be balanced at the bottom, whereby we have the Depth by weight, and the weight of what quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we pleaſe. Thus theſe inſtruments will be of ſervice for a thouſand uſes in Weighing, Meaſuring, Gaging, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying the Heights, Depths, Weights, Extentions of all manner of Liquids from one drop or grain of any thing, to a Fountain of Sea or Air, and by that means diſcover both their Quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Qualities.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the alterations of the weather; they are known by the variations of the weight of the Air according to the former Chapters, the Increaſe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of which variation I have not yet obſerved to be more than one in Twenty, Ten in two Hundred; or a Hundred in two Thouſand Parts, but will ſuppoſe it may alter a hundred and twenty in two Thouſand Parts, ſo that if a Cylinder, Cone, or other Particles of Air weighs now two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Grains, Scruples, Drachms, Oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Pounds, or Hundreds, it may ſometimes weigh two thouſand and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:50242:52"/>Sixty, and at other times not above one Thouſand Nine Hundred and Forty, (the reaſon why I make uſe of this number of weights, I have told in the Second Chapter.) The parts of which variation may be thus call'd
<table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Hard-froſt</cell>
                        <cell>Froſt</cell>
                        <cell>Froſt</cell>
                        <cell>Snovv</cell>
                        <cell>Rain</cell>
                        <cell>Rain</cell>
                        <cell>Changeable</cell>
                        <cell>Stormy</cell>
                        <cell>Fair</cell>
                        <cell>Set-fair</cell>
                        <cell>very-dry</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1940</cell>
                        <cell>1950</cell>
                        <cell>1960</cell>
                        <cell>1970</cell>
                        <cell>1980</cell>
                        <cell>1990</cell>
                        <cell>2000</cell>
                        <cell>2010</cell>
                        <cell>2020</cell>
                        <cell>2040</cell>
                        <cell>2060</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Hard-froſt</cell>
                        <cell>Froſt</cell>
                        <cell>Wet</cell>
                        <cell>very vvet</cell>
                        <cell>Rain</cell>
                        <cell>Cloudy</cell>
                        <cell>Changeable</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>Fair</cell>
                        <cell>Set-fair</cell>
                        <cell>very-dry</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:50242:53"/>
               <p>The words above the Figures as the Air grows heavier, and thoſe below it as the Air grows lighter, but for the exact knowledge of the weather, to foretell all the alterations in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity and quality, we muſt obſerve the rules in the following Chapter: And thus I have by two plain and eaſie Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ometrical Propoſitions ſhewn the manner, and now give the World leave to judge of the Probability, Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, and uſefulneſs of this Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in many other things, than can poſſibly be thought of, or applied to in this Age, and to conſider if they pleaſe, what it may lead to further in divers other reſpects, and what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions they may in time be able to make to it, for it is capable of many improvements, and will recompenſe the Induſtrious that underſtand it with ſeveral advantages in their own private buſineſs, if they beſtow but one tenth part of the time, pains, and coſt, upon it that I have done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:50242:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Rules for the more certain knowledge of all the alterations of weather, both in quantity and quality.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt, to have the Barometer alwaies with us, that we may alwaies know the weight of the Air, and how it has been two, three or four days before, whether growing lighter or heavier, and in what part of the variation it is. Then firſt in Summer it may weigh near 2060, and if it decreaſe 3 or 4 parts in 24 hours, it may hold till it comes to 2010, before it rains, which will be but little.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. If it decreaſe from about 2060, to 2040 in 24 hours or leſs, it will be windy, yet clear and dry, but it will hold but a little while, for it will ſoon increaſe again, but this ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom happens.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:50242:54"/>
               <p n="3">3dly. If it weighs 2040, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes 16, 18 or 20 parts in 24 hours the wind will blow, and it will rain a little, but it will be only a Storm, and after that it will increaſe again in an hour or two, and be fair.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly. If it weighs 2030 and decreaſe to 2020 in 18 or 24 hours, it will be windy for a day, but if it rain it will be only a ſmall ſhower or two of a few minutes continuance.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly. If it weighs about 2030 and decreaſe 2 or 3 parts in 18 or 24 hours, it may decreaſe to 1980 or leſs before it rains, which will then be for a whole day, with a ſoft driving wind.</p>
               <p n="6">6ly. If it weighs 2030, and decreaſe to 2000 in 18 or 24 hours it will Thunder, Lighten, Rain and Blow in a very violent manner, and pour down a Sea of water in a few hours, with terrible Diſploſions of Wind and Thunder, hardly to be diſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p n="7">7ly. If it weighs about 2030, 2026 or 24 and decreaſe to 1990, 1985, or 80, in 16 or 18 hours, it will be a moſt violent Hurricane with moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent Winds, Thunders and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:50242:54"/>as if the whole Heavens were on fire, with as violent rain poured down by whole Seas, for ſome hours or half a day together.</p>
               <p n="8">8ly. If it weighs about 2020, and decreaſes to 1980 in 18 or 24 hours it will Rain, Thunder and Lighten, and be as great a Tempeſt as we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly have in theſe parts, and may hold the bigeſt part of a day, or night as it begins.</p>
               <p n="9">9ly. If it weighs but 2010, and decreaſe to 1980 in 18 or 24 hours, it will Thunder and Lighten and be very Windy and Tempeſtous with large Hail and Rain, to the turning up of ſeveral Houſes and Trees, tho in <hi>January.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10ly. If it weighs about 2010, and decreaſe to 1980, 1975 or 70 in 12 or 16 hours it it will be Windy to a Miracle with little or no rain, but if it be 24 or 30 hours, in making this decreaſe it will then be Windy and Rainy with Hail and Thunder.</p>
               <p n="11">11. If it weighs about 2000, and decreaſe to 1980 or near the matter, in 18 or 24 hours it will be ſtormy
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:50242:55"/>with Rain and Hail and Winds, but calm intermiſſions.</p>
               <p n="12">12. If it weighs but 1990, and decreaſe to 1970, 65 or 60 in 18 or 24 hours, it will be very tempeſtuous with Wind, ſmall Hail, Rain and Thunder, but moſt Wind, and that Wind like Thunder.</p>
               <p n="13">13. If it weighs about 1990, and decreaſe 2 or 3 parts in 24 hours, if it decreaſe never ſo long it will rain all the while, but if it ſtands or increaſe a little, tho it weighs but 1970 or leſs it will be fair.</p>
               <p n="14">14. If it weighs but 1980, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe 2 or 3 parts in 24 hours there will be very cold Rain all the while, and if it weighs but 1970, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing it will Snow tho at Midſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and be very cold and very wet, more like Winter than Summer.</p>
               <p n="15">15. If it weighs but 1960 as, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not weigh much leſs two days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Summer, ſo we may be ſure it will be very cold wet and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly.</p>
               <p n="16">16. And from what weight ſoever it decreaſes 3 or 4 parts in 12 hours,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:50242:55"/>if it have ſtood 2 or 3 days before, it will be windy with freſh and pleaſant Gales: And if it increaſe 5 or 6 parts in 12 hours from any weight, after it have ſtood as before, it will be a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle windy.</p>
               <p>There ſhould be 3 or 4 Rules more for the increaſe, but that being for the moſt part fair or windy, except between 1980 and 2000, they may be omitted for the preſent: Thus for the decreaſing to the Winter, and tho Winter have brought it to ſo ſmall a weight, yet it will not hold, except it begins about 2000 or 1995 at leaſt.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Therefore if it continues to weigh 2000 or 1995 parts, two or 3 days in Winter, it will freeze, &amp; the longer it holds, of that weight the more, but if it increaſe 2 or 3 parts in 24 hours, two or three days together it will go away, and if it decreaſe two or three parts in 24 hours, it will continue and Freeze harder and harder, as long as it ſo decreaſes, till at laſt it may not weigh above 1945 or 1950, and yet it will be very fair and clear, but very ſharp
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:50242:56"/>Froſt as long as it holds of that weight</p>
               <p n="18">18. Thus being of the leaſt weight it can be, if it increaſe from 1945 or 50, to 1960 in 24 hours, it will be windy, but very clear and extreme ſharp and freezing; and ſo alſo if the weight decreaſe from 1960 to 1950 or leſs in 24 hours time, it will be ſuch a freezing wind, but if it increaſe or decreaſe but one or two parts in 24 hours between theſe two, there will be very little alterations, only clear and freezing.</p>
               <p n="19">19. If it increaſe from 1960 to 1970 in 24 hours, it will Snow the next day in Storms, but it will ſoon be over, and decreaſe again, but if it increaſe from 1960, 2 or 3 parts in 24 hours till it weighs 1970, or 1975, it will Snow conſiderably, and if in Snowing the weight increaſe, it will Snow the more, but if it decreaſe it will be the leſs.</p>
               <p n="20">20. If it increaſe from 1970 to 1980, or 1985 in 24 hours time, it will be very windy, and at laſt Rain, and then decreaſe again, and Thaw,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:50242:56"/>but if it increaſe again, the Froſt will not remain, as it will notwithſtanding the rain if it decreaſe, and if it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe 2 or parts in 24 hours till it weighs 1980 or 85 the froſt will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly go with plenty of rain.</p>
               <p n="21">21. If it increaſe from 1980 to 1990 it will be fair and freeze again, and if it increaſe 2 or 3 parts in 24 hours will hold till it weighs 2318 or 2020, but then it will grow warm and miſty (firſt thawing in the Air) and the froſt will go away without rain, nay ſo much without, that it will be fair and clear all the while it is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tho in the midſt of Winter.</p>
               <p n="22">22. If it increaſe from 1999 to 2000 in 12 or 16 hours it will be windy the ſame day, and then decreaſe a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and rain the next, but if it increaſe but a little it will hold fair and be calm.</p>
               <p n="23">23. If it increaſe from 2000 to 2020, 2030, or 40 in 18 or 24 hours it will be windy, but fair, yet rain the next day by ſtorms, and after that a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled warm rain, but if it increaſes leiſurely it will hold fair all the while.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:50242:57"/>
               <p n="24">24. If it increaſe to a bigger weight, it will be more like Summer than Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, very fair clear and warm, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any froſt. The truth of all which is very plain from the former Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the following Experiments.</p>
               <p>In <hi>December</hi> 1696, when I was ſure I could weigh and meaſure any parcel of Air, obſerving ſome alterations of weather, that I could not then give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſon for, I bought a common Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rometer or Quickſilver-Glaſs, and then an Hermetick Thermometer, by which I made ſeveral other ſorts to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare my own, and all their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with the alterations of the weather in a Diary, which I continued to <hi>June</hi> 1699, on the 12 of <hi>January</hi> 96/7 a froſt began (which proved to be the hardeſt ſince the great one, 13 years before;) the Air weighed that day 1996 and continued with very little alteration till the 16th, after which it decreaſed 2 or 3 parts, and ſometimes 4 in 24 hours, to the end of the month, when it weighed but 1950; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>February</hi> it increaſed a little and weighed 1962; on the fourth when there was ſo ſharp a freez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:50242:57"/>wind, that my hand on the Iron handle of a Pail or Well-Bucket, it would cleave ſo faſt to it that it was ready to pull off the skin to take my hand off again, or to try with my fing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as ſeveral others did, by dabbing on a freſh place of the Iron, it immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtuck ſo faſt it made it very ſore to pull off, and could not indure to do it above a time or two. After the fourth it decreaſed again till the ſeventh, when it weighed but a little above 1949, where it continued 12 days to the 19th, and was very ſharp, but after that it began to inceraſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſlowly, till the 6th of <hi>March,</hi> when it weighed 1968, and went a way a few days after. About the 20th of <hi>January</hi> when the weight of the Air was abated about 19 parts, and the Quickſilver ſunk between three and four tenths, I began to think the weather would alter in a few days to Rain or Snow, but weighing thus till the end of the month, the Air growing lighter and lighter all the while, and the Quickſilver at laſt near half way below Rain, and yet the weather clear, and more ſharp and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:50242:58"/>freezing by the Hermetick Thermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter, was I thought the ſtrangeſt thing that could happen, I therefore weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and meaſured ſeveral quantities or particles of Air, in Cylinders, Cones, Globes and other figures of ſeveral dementions, ſome times 18 or 20 times in a day in ſeveral diſtant pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Tops of Hills, Vallies, Deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wells, Mines, and Coal-pits, warm fire Rooms, Stoves, and open Air; And thus at laſt with a great deal of Pains and Coſt found the Air it ſelf was frozen, and thereby kept off the Superiour Gravitation, and by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe means, the reaſons of all the other alterations of weather as well hot as cold, wet and dry, Wind, and Thunder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>November</hi> the 28th 1697, a little froſt began of about 8 days, that day the Air weighed 1972, the 30th it weighed 1997, the 3d of <hi>December</hi> it weighed 2022, the 5th 2034, being very fair all the while (and froze very hard about the 1d and 2d) the next day it grew warm, but then decreaſed to 2003 in 24 hours, there was firſt a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Snow, then ſmall Rain, and the froſt went away.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:50242:58"/>
               <p>But <hi>December</hi> the 3d 1698 having been froſty for ſometime, the weight of the Air increaſed to 2020, the 4th was very fair yet thawed apace, the mornings and evenings a little miſty with the thaw, but otherways very clear and ſo went away without any Rain.</p>
               <p>The 29th. of <hi>October</hi> at night 1697 the Air weighed 2018 the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it weighed but 1996, the day was very windy but no Rain.</p>
               <p>But the effects of the Greateſt wind that have been for many years are rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the 5th Chapter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April</hi> the 10th 1699, the Air weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but 1978, the 11th it weighed 1996, there was firſt a little ſmall rain, but after that very windy, the 12th in the morning at ſix it weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 2018, at 10 but 1990, at 12 1988, about 3 or 4 in the afternoon, being near <hi>Maidenhead,</hi> there was a very ſtrange and unuſual Tempeſt in the adjacent parts of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and <hi>Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> of Wind and Thunder and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, with Hail, and Rain, with that violence or ſtrangeneſs, that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploſive Crackes of Wind and Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:50242:59"/>were hardly to be diſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>April the</hi> 16th following, being near <hi>London</hi> at noon the Air weighed 2005, at 9 at night but 1987, the 17th at 6 in the morning it weighed but 1970, about 2 afternoon it began to be a little Stormy, and at 4 a great Tempeſt of Thunder and Lightning, Hail and Rain. I have many other remarkable alterations of Rain, Snow, Cold, Hot, Wet and Dry weather, but reſerve them with the ſeveral other things for another opportunity.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="addenda">
            <pb facs="tcp:50242:59"/>
            <head>ADDENDA.</head>
            <p>SInce the former ſheets were in the Preſs the continual uſe of this Barome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter has diſcover'd ſeveral other things that former Ages were uſed to think too Good for their Enemies, or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, which, may be, was the Reaſon that have hindred us from thoſe Advantages: Some of theſe are, Firſt, the true Cauſe or Reaſon of the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea, in ſo plain and ſatisfactory a manner, that it leaves no room for the leſt ſcruple about it, and Salves all the Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances (with Mathematical Certainty) of that hitherto unknown mighty work of nature, why the higheſt and loweſt Spring and Nape Tides, are Conſtantly about three days after the Change, Full and Quarters of the Moon; And why the Spring and
<pb facs="tcp:50242:60"/>Nape Tides are ſo much greater in March and September than at any other time of the year, And why there is 15 or 16 Foot Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween high and low Water in ſome Places, and not above 3 or 4 in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: And though I have neither had neither time nor opportunity to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, ſince I Diſcover'd it, yet I am ſure it is not the Moons being upon a Certain Meridian that makes it high or low Water at that time, the ſame day, but a Particular and Proper Diſtance of the Sun and Moon, 24 hours, or more, before that time, All which is as Plain as the Tides are viſible.</p>
            <p>And immediately after it diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the true Reaſon of the Magnetick Needles Pointing to the North and South, and of its variations: And that many other things ſo Placed will have the ſame Tendences, as I ſoon Experienc'd. After which, I tried ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others Exactly fitted in as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fluid Currents, which all ſtood the ſame way: For if they were nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fitted in true Aequilibrium, and Both Ends of equal diſtance from the
<pb facs="tcp:50242:60"/>Centre they would not Point but Lie Croſs the Current: But if being in Aquilibrium, one End were longer than the other, they would not lie Croſs, but Point, and which End that was, may eaſily be gueſs'd. From whence we may be ſure the Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude Can never be truly found by the Variation, or the Variation of the Variation, as ſome have thought.</p>
            <p>It has Diſcover'd ſeveral other things about the Prime and original Cauſe of Winds, Rain, Hail, Froſt, Snow, Thunder, and other Meteors: what it is that gives the Air that motion we call Wind originally, and what Gathers Clowds, and Condenſes the Effluvia into Rain, That it is not the influence of <g ref="char:male">♂</g> or ♃, nor the Cente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral motion of the Sun, nor always the Latitude of the Place that makes Warm or Cold Weather: But that the Cloudes do always Concenturate the Sun Beams to make Thunder, with a further moſt Plain and Senſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Demonſtration of the Influence of the Stars (that are ſo ſweet and bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in their Courſes fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Siſera</hi>) in all Reſpects as Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb facs="tcp:50242:61"/>as we ſee and know the Blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Wind. Theſe if Life and Leiſure laſt, will at ſome time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come abroad, either by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or in another Edition of this, to which by their Diſcovery they do more Properly belong.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subscription_offer">
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:50242:61"/>
            <p>IN the mean time, if any Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Merchants, Seamen or others, deſire any of theſe Porta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Barometers, as They are of real worth in all proceeding ways, and for many other Diſcoveries, and have been very chargeable, ſo they will not be parted with but by Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, for a Thouſand to pay one Guinee a peace down, for as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as the Subſcriber intends to have, to Mr — whom I ſhall be obliged to give a diſcharge, and return the Money if they be not De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in three months after Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, but upon delivering the Barometers the Subſcribe to pay half a Guinea a piece more, for as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as he has ſubſcribed for. So the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:50242:62"/>Subſcribers ſhall have them Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, as eaſily Portable in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as a Knife and Fork, or ſome Ink-Horns, and as ſeeure to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried any where, that neither the heat of the Body, Fire, nor Air, (except put into the Fire) Froſt, nor Wet, can any ways alter. Which if ſecured from other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers would not be ſold under two or three Guineas.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:50242:62"/>
            <head>THE Table or Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> WHat the Portable Barometer is, the Conſtitution of the Atmoſphere, and that the Effluvia keep off the Airs Gravitation, and are the Cauſe of the variation of its weight. <hi>Pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> How Rain and Snow is Generated and Produced, and why they make a Cylinder of Air lighter, and yet any other particular parcel of Air much heavier. <hi>Pag. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> How Winds, Storms, Tempeſts, Hurricanes, and Tornados are produced. <hi>Pag. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> That violent Tempeſts, Hurricanes, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nados ſeldom happen in cold Countries, Winter Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, large Plains or Great Seas. <hi>Pag. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> That they are eaſily foretold, becauſe they produce the greateſt variations, in the weight of Air. <hi>Pag. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> What froſt and Thunder is, a Conjecture at their Cauſes and Productions. <hi>Pag. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> That there never is no ſettled Froſt to hold when the Air continues to weigh <hi>2020</hi> or more,
<pb facs="tcp:50242:63"/>nor never no Thunder when it weighs but <hi>1980</hi> or leſs. <hi>Pag. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> That tho a Cylinder of Air weight much leſs in wet or windy weather than it does in dry weather, yet in a ſettled froſt tho the Air appears never ſo clear and dry, it weighs much leſs than at any other time. <hi>Pag. 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> Whether the Planetary Beams or Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences can cauſe an alteration of the weather to be foretold by them. <hi>Pag. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> That it is impoſſible by an Hygroſcope, Thermometer, or other Invention to know the true ſtate of the Air. <hi>Pag. 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> The uſe of the Portable Barometer, how to weigh the Air, Meaſure its Height, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell all the alterations of weather. <hi>Pag. 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> Rules for the more certain knowledge of all the alterations of weather both in quantity and quality. <hi>pag. 91.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:50242:63"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>W. Hawes,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A True Account of <hi>Germany,</hi> its Strength, and Power; together with a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of War and Peace, with Remarks and Maxims of <hi>Charles</hi> V. late Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> General of the Emperor's Forces. From a Manuſcript left by him, and never Printed before.</p>
            <p>A New <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dictionary with the Terms of Gypſies, Beggers, Thieves, Cheats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for all ſorts of People (eſpecially Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) to ſecure their Money, and preſerve their Lives, beſide, very Diverting and Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, never Printed before. by <hi>Edward Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>Ten Pleaſant and Delightful Novels, VIZ.
<list>
                  <item>Rival Ladies.</item>
                  <item>The Miſtake.</item>
                  <item>The Generous Lover.</item>
                  <item>The Libertine</item>
                  <item>The Virgin Captive.</item>
                  <item>The Perfidious Miſtreſs.</item>
                  <item>The Metamorphos'd Lover.</item>
                  <item>The Impoſter out Witted.</item>
                  <item>The Amorous Miſer.</item>
                  <item>The Pretended Alchymiſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Being Collected and Printed in 1. Voll.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
